Finding Aid for Employment Transition Program (University of Michigan) records, 1979-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Employment Transition Program (University of Michigan) records 1979-1998
University of Michigan. Employment Transition Program.
8.5 linear feet
0093 Bimu 2
The Employment Transition Program (ETP) was an applied and experimental program focusing on employment relationships, particularly in the automobile industry. ETP was one of the initial grant-funded studies and came to serve as an umbrella title for several subsequent grants including studies involving the United Auto Workers and Ford Motor Company. ETP was established by Jeanne P. Gordus. ETP records include grant proposals (funded and non-funded), training manuals, publications, and project development files relating to studies on unemployment and intervention training programs for displaced auto workers, including life education planning programs and life education advisors.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred to the Bentley Library in February 1998 (donor no. 8690 ).
The collection is open for research.
The Employment Transition Program (ETP) began on September 1, 1982. The original project, a three-year intervention in the unemployment experience, was administered by Jeanne Prial Gordus and was a test of whether it was possible to substantially reduce the period between involuntary job loss and re-employment.
The name of the first project, ETP, stuck with the group of professionals and students who came to the Industrial Development Division in 1983 to conduct research with Gordus. Thereafter, ETP was an umbrella term used to group a number of projects having the same job search and career change objectives. These projects were directed at unionized, blue-collar workers, through enhancement of personal, educational, and vocational skills. Projects also sought ways to prevent the harmful physical and mental health effects often associated with prolonged unemployment.
Although the ETP conducted many projects across many industries, it focused primarily on autoworkers. This collection of materials best documents the Life/Education Planning Program (L/EPP), which was a twelve-year joint project of the University of Michigan, Ford Motor Company, and the United Auto Workers (UAW) from 1985 to 1998. L/EPP was grant funded by the United States Department of Education, Fund for the Improvement of Post-Secondary Education. The Ford Motor Company and UAW-Ford provided other funding.
The goal of L/EPP was much the same as the goal of the overall ETP program: to provide training, retraining, and developmental opportunities to both active and displaced autoworkers. The purpose of the program was to stimulate the involvement of workers in a comprehensive range of educational, personal development, and training opportunities. In order to accomplish this goal, the ETP recruited and trained Life Education Advisors (LEA). An LEA was assigned to one or more Ford plants, depending on plant size. The LEAs worked with community colleges, technical schools, and vocational training centers to develop classes for the plant workers. The LEAs also counseled the plant workers on class selection and helped to make them aware of the opportunities that continuing education and personal development classes offered them. They assisted the workers in identifying their personal goals and helped them develop plans to attain these goals. At the height of the L/EPP project, there were approximately 60 LEAs working in UAW-Ford plants in the states of Michigan, Ohio, Illinois, Indiana, and Missouri.
The role of the University of Michigan was threefold: 1) to employ professionals from human service fields to provide education services and programs to union represented workers; 2) to monitor program progress; and 3) to conduct research on program effectiveness and the impact of in-plant advisory service. The University of Michigan linked its mission with the L/EPP through research and service. The design of this research provided the opportunity to observe, analyze, and interpret data important to several fields (psychology, sociology, and economics). The university also provided service to non-students while acting as a facilitator by enhancing human investment in Michigan's then current workforce.
Plant workers were not required to participate in the program, however most did and the program was undoubtedly a success. During its lifetime, the program won several awards. In 1987 it was recognized by United States Department of Education as one of the most promising guidance programs in the United States at the time.
The ETP began in the Industrial Development Division, under the direction of Jeanne Gordus. She and the program moved to the Institute for Science and Technology in 1983 and then finally to the School of Social Work in 1988. Gordus directed the ETP until her death of cancer in 1990. Robert Toronto, a professor in the School of Social Work, succeeded her and was director until the program's end in 1998. Larry Root, Professor of Social Work, was the co-director of the L/EPP from 1988-1990.
The Employment Transition Program (ETP) records include grant proposals (funded and non-funded), training manuals, publications, and project development files relating to studies on unemployment and intervention training programs for displaced auto workers, including life education planning programs and life education advisors. The record group is organized into four series: Grant Proposals, Project Development Files, Publications, and Contracts. The activities of the Employment Transition Project (ETP) are best documented in Grant Proposals and Publications. The activities of the Life/Education Planning Program (L/EPP) from 1985 to 1998 are best documented in Contracts.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Employment Transition Program.; Employees--Training of--Michigan.; Occupational training--Michigan.; Occupational retraining--Michigan.; Plant shutdowns.; Career education--Michigan.; Unemployed--Michigan.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan.; Labor unions--Michigan.; Ford Motor Company--Personnel management.; Employees--Relocation.; Gordus, Jeanne P.; Automobile industry workers--Labor unions--United States.
Contributors:
Gordus, Jeanne P.
- Grant Proposals
  The Grant Proposals series contains funded as well as un-funded proposals. The proposal descriptions offer a good overview of ETP projects, their goals, objectives, and accomplishments. These proposals are also meant to give the researcher an idea of what types of unemployment studies granting institutions were funding and not funding during the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Employment Transition Program
    - Funded Proposals
      - 1981 (Box 1)
      - 1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1993 (Box 1)
      - 1996 (Box 1)
    - Not Funded Proposals
      - 1982, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1983 (Box 2)
      - 1984 (Box 2)
      - 1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986 (Box 2)
      - 1988 (Box 2)
      - 1989 (Box 2)
  - Related Proposals
    - 1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1986-1988 (Box 2)
- Project Development Files
  Project Development Files contains ETP and L/EPP history, some meeting information, and L/EPP data. This data summarizes the effectiveness of the LEAs and the overall plant response to the L/EPP project. The plant reviews, case studies, and year-end plant reports in this series contain information on the number of workers taking advantage of the program and consulting the plant LEA.
  - History
    - Background Information (Box 2)
    - Clippings 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Employment Transition Program 1984-1990 (Box 2)
    - Goals/Accomplishments 1991-1998 (Box 2)
    - Jeanne Prial Gordus (Box 2)
    - Transition Minutes 1995-1997 (Box 2)
  - Life/Education Planning Program
    - Class Description, Fall 1988 (Box 2)
    - Human Subject Research Information (Box 2)
    - L/EPP Overview (Box 2)
    - "Linking the Mission of UM with L/EPP" (Box 2)
    - Management Structure of L/EPP 1986 (Box 2)
    - Press Release, "New UAW-Ford Program Stresses Education" (Box 2)
  - Meetings
    - University of Michigan-United Auto Workers-Ford Quarterly Life/Education Planning Program (L/EPP) meetings 1989-1991, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Life/Education Planning Program (L/EPP) team meetings
      - 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1997-1998, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - NEDTC L/EPP team and UM L/EPP staff 1994 (Box 3)
  - Memos and Correspondence
    - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - 1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - Communication 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Focus Groups 1991 (Box 3)
    - Life Education Advisors (LEA) Monitoring 1992 (Box 3)
    - Best Practices 1995 (Box 3)
    - LEA Learning Resource Network 1995 (Box 3)
    - LEA New Hire Initiatives undated (Box 3)
    - Promotions undated (Box 3)
  - Plant Reports
    - Comparison Reports 1992-1995, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Case Studies 1986 (Box 3)
    - Reviews 1995 (alphabetical by plant name)
      - A-G (Box 3)
      - H-M (Box 3)
      - N-R (Box 4)
      - S (Box 4)
      - T-Z (Box 4)
    - Year-End Reports
      - 1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1995, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1997, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Publications
  Directors Gordus and Toronto were extremely prolific. As a result, the Publications series contains many articles documenting the findings and progress of the Life/Education Planning Program (L/EPP) from a number of different social welfare perspectives. It also contains Life Education Advisors (LEA) training manuals and, at the end of the series, a nearly complete run of LEA newsletters. Also included are relevant reports and articles, authored by Jeanne Gordus, that pre-date the ETP altogether. Finally, the series contains documentation of a few smaller projects that took place concurrently with the L/EPP, such as a telephone survey of the educational wants and needs of employees in a Cadillac plant. Publications are arranged alphabetically by year, with undated materials at the end of the series.
  - 1978-1980
    - "Employment Relationship: Notes and Commentary on Issues in Labor and Industrial Relations," 1978-1979 (volume 1) (Box 5)
    - "Employment Relationship: Notes and Commentary on Issues in Labor and Industrial Relations," 1978-1979 (volume 2) (Box 5)
    - "Mental Health and the Economy," 1979 (Box 5)
  - 1981-1985
    - "Mental Health and the Economy: Implications for Current Practice and Future Research," 1981 (Box 5)
    - "Robotics: How will it Affect Society?," 1982 (Box 5)
    - "University of Michigan Institutional Grant Project: Final Report," 1982 (Box 5)
    - "Fund for the Improvement of Post-Secondary Education (FIPSE) Preliminary Reports," 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - "Participative Career Development: A Concept Paper Presented to the UAW-GM Regional Employee Training Development Program," 1983 (Box 5)
    - "Comparative Analysis of Responses to Industrial Displacement...," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Coping with Unemployment," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Displaced Labor and the Grand Haven AP Parts Plant Closing," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Economic Change, Physical Illness, Mental Illness, and Social Deviance," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "ETP Work Book," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "An Evaluation Design and Management Information System for the UAW-Ford Active Employee L/EPP and Education Program," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Human Resource Implications of Plant Shut-downs," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Impact of Michigan Bio-technology Institute on Employment in the City of Lansing," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Labor Force Status, Program Participation, and Economic Adjustment of Displaced Auto Workers," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Michigan Program Inventory," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Pre-layoff Intervention: A Response to Unemployment," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Prospectus for Needs Assessment/Goal Attainment Study of UAW-Ford Active Workers," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Saginaw Valley Model Part 1: Tri-County Region Labor Needs Survey," 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Unemployment and Re-employment Experiences of Michigan Auto Workers 1984 (Box 5)
    - "Combined UAW-Ford Programs: College and University Options Program and L/EPP: Plan for Implementation," 1985 (Box 5)
    - "Displaced Workers and Adjustment Resources," 1985 (Box 5)
    - "FIPSE Final Report," 1985 (Box 5)
    - "Screening, Selection and Program Implementation: Overview for Entry Process for Life Education Advisors, 1985" (Box 5)
    - "Tracking UAW-represented/Ford Hourly Employees...," 1985 (Box 5)
    - "UAW-Ford L/EPP Information Package, 1985" (Box 5)
    - ""UAW-Ford L/EPP Manual for Employee Advisors, Modules 1-26, 1985" (Box 5)
    - "UAW-Ford L/EPP Preliminary Report, 1985" (Box 5)
    - "Unemployment and Mental Health," 1985 (Box 5)
  - 1986-1989
    - "College and University Options Program," 1986 (Box 5)
    - "Coping with Involuntary Job Loss and Building a New Career: Workers' Problems and Career Professionals Challenges," 1985 (Box 5)
    - "Economic Losses of Laid-Off Auto Workers," 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - "Incomparable Losses: Economic and Labor Market Outcomes for Unemployed Female versus Male Autoworkers," 1986 (Box 5)
    - "L/EPP Survey Wave 1," 1986 (Box 5)
    - "UAW-Ford Employee Development and Training: A Case Study of Two Program Approaches," 1986 (Box 5)
    - "UAW-Ford Life/Education Planning Program: an Interim Report," 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - "UAW-Ford Life/Education Planning Program Research Plan," 1986 (Box 5)
    - "Women's Work and Technological Change: Career Prospects in the Information Society," 1986 (Box 5)
    - "Employment Transition Program: Design, Implementation, and Evaluation of an Unemployment Intervention," 1987 (Box 5)
    - "Joint UAW-Ford Employee Development," 1987 (Box 5)
    - "Permanent Dislocation and Adjustment Strategies: a Literature and Program Review," 1987 (Box 5)
    - "Preventing Obsolescence Through Retraining: Contexts, Policies, and Programs," 1987 (Box 5)
    - "Proposed Center Report on the Life/Education Planning Program," 1987 (Box 5)
    - "Story of UAW-Ford Life/Education Planning Program," 1987 (Box 5)
    - "Cadillac Telephone Survey Data," 1988 (Box 5)
    - "Contact Summaries and their Use in Assessing Life Education Advisor (LEA) Effectiveness," 1988 (Box 5)
    - "Costs of Structural Change," 1988 (Box 6)
    - "L/EPP Reporting as Seen in Contract Summaries," 1988 (Box 6)
    - "Organizational Learning and Adversity," 1988 (Box 6)
    - "Retraining Experiences and Outcomes: the Case of Displaced Autoworkers," 1988 (Box 6)
    - "Autoworkers in Transition: a Case Study Dislocation, Experiences, and Outcomes," 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Exploring the Adult Education Participation Patterns of Male Industrial Workers," 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Future of Work and Workers in America," 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Open Letter to Hydreco Survey Respondents," 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Promoting Personal and Organizational Change," 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Restructuring of the American Auto Industry: Lessons for the Reduction in Armament Production," 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Unemployment and Education: Adjustment Strategies for Displaced Workers," 1989 (Box 6)
  - 1990-1998
    - "L/EPP Survey Wave 2," 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "Coming Back: What's different and what's the same," 1990 (Box 6)
    - "Comparison of Characteristics of Autoworkers who take Hands-on Classes with those who take Academic Classes," 1990 (Box 6)
    - "Six-Year Progress Report on the UAW-Ford Life/Education Planning Program," 1991 (Box 6)
    - "UAW-Ford L/EPP Concurrent Session," 1992 (Box 6)
    - "Developing a Learning Workforce," 1993 (Box 6)
    - "Race, Seniority, and Education in Blue Collar Re-employment," 1993 (Box 6)
    - "Trends and Patterns of Worker/LEA Interaction," 1993 (Box 6)
    - "UM Supplemental Policies and Administrative Procedures for Life Education Advisors," 1993 (Box 6)
    - "Increasing Participation in Adult Education: Analysis of an Experimental Program in the Workplace," 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Intergenerational Pilot Study Report," 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Workforce Education: the UAW-Ford L/EPP," 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Reframing Concepts of Development in the Contexts of Social Change," 1994 (Box 6)
    - "Completion Rates of UAW-represented Ford Employees in On-site Classes," 1995 (Box 6)
    - "I was an Eleeaye," 1997 (Box 6)
    - "Twelve-Year Historical Report," 1998, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Undated
    - "Analysis of Defense Manufacturing Employment in Michigan by Occupational Groups and a Survey of Associated Unemployment Benefits," undated (Box 7)
    - "Analysis of Participation in Adult Education: Findings from a Quasi-Experimental Study," undated (Box 7)
    - "Analysis of Program Participation in the Employment Transition Program," undated (Box 7)
    - "Attribution, Responsibility, and Outcomes: Seeking Meaning in the Unemployment Research Literature," undated (Box 7)
    - "Asking Around: 32 Questions about the Future of Work and your Working Future," undated (Box 7)
    - "Automobile Workers and the American Dream Re-visited," undated (Box 7)
    - "Context of Structural Change and Adjustment in the American Auto Industry," undated (Box 7)
    - "Continuous Flow Model for Community Development Responses," undated (Box 7)
    - "Data on Adult Education from Public and Private Sources for Comparison with the UAW-Ford Programs," undated (Box 7)
    - "Double Binds in Unemployment and Services for the Unemployed," undated (Box 7)
    - "Economic and Labor Market Impacts of Massive Layoffs on Women and Families," undated (Box 7)
    - "Economic Outcomes for Dislocated Older Workers," undated (Box 7)
    - "Education Fair Manual," undated (Box 7)
    - "Employee Development and Training Program Learning Centers," undated (Box 7)
    - "ETP Manual for Trainers," undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - "Evaluating Dislocation Intervention for Different Employment Categories," undated (Box 7)
    - "Exploring Work as an Arena for Prevention Research," undated (Box 7)
    - "Features and Characteristics of Location Onsite Degree Programs," undated (Box 7)
    - "History of Chicago Regional Consortium for Experiential Learning," undated (Box 7)
    - "How the UAW-Ford L/EPP Works," undated (Box 7)
    - "Joint Programs for Lifelong Learning," undated (Box 7)
    - "LEA Directory," undated (Box 7)
    - "LEA Program Initiatives," undated (Box 7)
    - "L/EPP Center Report #6," undated (Box 7)
    - "Management Information System Report," undated (Box 7)
    - "Michigan Displaced Auto Workers Study," undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - "Personal and Occupational Dependence on Defense Contracting," undated (Box 7)
    - "Plant Closings, Worker Dislocation, and Retraining," undated (Box 7)
    - "Program Participation and Compensation for Displaced Autoworkers," undated (Box 7)
    - "Promoting Personal and Organizational Change," undated (Box 7)
    - "Public and Private Income Maintenance and Adjustment Programs Available to Displaced Autoworkers," undated (Box 7)
    - "Qualitative Experiences of Program Participants," undated (Box 7)
    - "Regional and Occupational Dependence on Defense Contracting," undated (Box 7)
    - "Restructuring of the American Auto Industry Progress Report," undated (Box 7)
    - "Tale of Two Plant Closings," undated (Box 7)
    - "UAW-Ford L/EPP: an Eight-Year Perspective," undated (Box 7)
    - "Unemployed Experience: what's going on and what to do," undated (Box 7)
    - "Women in CETA: the Social Context of Public Service Employment," undated (Box 7)
    - "Women in Management: Position and Prospects," undated (Box 7)
    - Life Education Advisors (LEA) Newsletters 1988-1990 (Box 7)
    - Life Education Advisors (LEA) Newsletters 1990-1997, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Contracts -- Life/Education Planning Program (L/EPP)
  Contracts, the last series, are arranged chronologically from 1985 to 1998. Each contract period maintained materials related to the contract itself, while some years also included contract -related documentation, subcontract information, transition and pilot information, correspondence and meeting notes.
  - Year 1 02/15/1985-07/14/1986, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Year 1 02/15/1985-07/14/1986 ITI Subcontract, Consultants, NEDTC, EDTP, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Year 1 02/15/1985-07/14/1986 Contract-Related Documentation, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Year 2 07/15/1986-07/14/1987 (Box 8)
  - Year 2 07/15/1986-07/14/1987 Contract-Related Documentation (Box 8)
  - Year 3 07/15/1987-08/14/1988, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Year 3 07/15/1987-08/14/1988 Contract-Related Documentation (Box 8)
  - Years 4, 5 08/15/1988-08/14/1990, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Years 4, 5 08/15/1988-08/14/1990 PDC and Ford/New Holland Locations (Box 8)
  - Years 6, 7, 8 07/01/1990-06/30/1993, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Years 6, 7, 8 07/01/1990-06/30/1993 Program Review Pilot, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Years 9, 10, 11 07/01/1993-10/31/1996, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Years 9, 10, 11 07/01/1993-10/31/1996 Contract-Related Documentation, Correspondence (Box 9)
  - Years 9, 10, 11 07/01/1993-10/31/1996 Email Pilot (Box 9)
  - Years 12, 13 11/01/1996-02/06/1998 Transition Plan, Layoff, Related Activities, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Years 12, 13 11/01/1996-02/06/1998 Contracts and Early Termination (Box 9)
  - Years 12, 13 11/01/1996-02/06/1998 Meeting Notes and Draft Proposals (Box 9)